<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The generall-good to all people: or, The Lords free love running forth freely to his own people in these latter days, according to his promises made to his people, which he is now fulfilling. With something in answer to the petition put up to the Parliament, by many of the city and county of York, even they of the priests party. / By Richard Farnworth.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E703_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E703_6*</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50796658</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50796658</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166593</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166593)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E703[6] or 108:E703[6*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The generall-good to all people: or, The Lords free love running forth freely to his own people in these latter days, according to his promises made to his people, which he is now fulfilling. With something in answer to the petition put up to the Parliament, by many of the city and county of York, even they of the priests party. / By Richard Farnworth.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
                  <author>Aldam, Thomas, d. 1660. Exhortation to the magistrates.</author>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666. Gods covenanting with his people.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the sign of the Black-spread Eagle at the West-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Gods covenanting with his people" has separate t.p., but continuous register and pagination; filmed separately at reel 108:E.703[6*].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>An exhortation to the magistrates / by Thomas Aldam -- An exhortation to all people that have desire to know the truth, that the truth may make them free / written by a Husbandman -- Gods covenanting with his people / by Richard Farnworth.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Yorkshire --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Yorkshire (England) --  Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166593:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Generall-Good To all PEOPLE: OR, The Lords free love running forth freely to his own people in theſe latter days, according to his promiſes made to his people, which he is now fulfilling.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 15.20, 21. 1 Pet 4.13, 14. Luke 6.22, 23. Mat. 5.10, 11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And that is the reaſon why the world hateth them, but it is but that the Scriptures may be fulfilled, as he hath ſaid, Ye ſhall be hated of all men, for my names ſake; Bleſſed are you, when men ſhall hate you, and revile you, and ſay all manner of evil againſt you; Rejoyce, and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven; Bleſſed are you that ſuffer for righteouſneſs ſake, for yours is the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>WITH</hi> Something in anſwer to the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition put up to the Parliament, by many of the City and County of <hi>York,</hi> even they of the Prieſts Party.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Farnworth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the Black-ſpread <hi>Eagle</hi> at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:166593:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:166593:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was moved to write this enſuing Treatiſe in the behalf of a harmleſs and innocent People, who are hated of the world, but beloved of the Lord, with whom my life is, which the world ſcorneth, and derideth, and ſpeaketh evil of, both Priſts and People, but it is becauſe they know not God; for thoſe that know him, cannot but ſpeak well of his name, and are made content to ſuffer for his names ſake, as thou mayeſt ſee, if thou do but read this Paper put into thy hand, what ſuffering Objects theſe are, that are thus reproached and reviled, and are not willing only to believe, but alſo to ſuffer for his name ſake, with whom I am made to bear the burden; Therefore did I write this in the behalf of thoſe that are the ſuffering Objects as well as my ſelf; and as it is my
<pb facs="tcp:166593:3"/>
bounden duty to declare againſt all deceits and deceivers, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but diſcharge my duty in declaring againſt all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whatſoever; and am I become your Enemy becauſe I tell you the truth? If you cannot receive me, receive the truth for the truths ſake, that you may know the truth, that the truth may ſet you free.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>York-ſhire.</hi>
                  <date>April. <hi>1653.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Richard Farnworth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166593:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The general good to all People:</hi> OR, The Lord making known the exceeding riches of his love to his people in theſe latter days.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord is now trying his people, as Gold is tried in the fire: Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Behold I will ſend my meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and he ſhall prepare the way before me; Even the meſſenger of the Covenant whom ye delight in; Behold he ſhall come to his Temple; but who ſhall abide the day of his comming? For he ſhall ſit as a refiner, and with refiners fire will he purge and purifie the ſons of Levi, that they may offer unto the Lord an offering in righteouſneſs:</hi> Then ſhall the offerings of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be pleaſant, and acceptable unto the Lord, and at that time ſhall <hi>Michael</hi> ſtand up, the great Prince which ſtandeth for the Children of thy People, and there ſhall be a time of trouble, ſuch as never was ſince there was a Nation, even to that ſame time; and at that time thy People ſhall be delivered, <hi>Every one that ſhall be found written in the Book. Daniel</hi> 12.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hear ye this O prieſts, and hearken ye houſe of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſea. 5.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>and give ye ear O houſe of the King; for judgement is toward you, becauſe ye have been a Snare on</hi> Miz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pah, <hi>and a Net ſpread upon</hi> Tabor; And the Revolters are profound to make ſlaughter, though I have been a rebuker of them all, yet they will not frame their doings to turn unto their God; for the ſpirit of whoredom is in the midſt of them, committing Fornication with many lovers, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wayes of <hi>Balaam,</hi> teaching for gifts and rewards, teaching for hire, and loving this preſent evil world, and are exceeding proud, and covetous, and cannot be content with their wages, to take ſuch as is ſet before them; for the workman is worthy of his meat: but they are not content, except
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166593:4"/>
they have great fat benefices, to be Lords and rulers over Gods heritage, feeding themſelves with the fat, and cloathing them with the wool, as the falſe Prophets and falſe ſhepherds did, that <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was ſent to cry out againſt, which God was diſpleaſed with, as he is now with all the falſe Prieſts, even all the Prieſts in <hi>England</hi> that follow the ſame practiſe, who are ſo covetous, that they oppreſs poor people, and do burden them, ſo that many groan under their burden of oppreſſion, by the luſtfull proud Prieſts; and they have their wives to go in their Hoods, Vails, Pride and Pomp, as the Mincing daughters of Iſrael did, which forgot the Lord, and he ſent his true Prophet to cry out againſt them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. as he doth to cry out againſt theſe Hirelings, Prieſts, and proud Prelates, with their Idols, and Images of Clay, which they ſet up for men to worſhip, feet of Clay, leggs of Braſs, and breſts of Silver, and head of Gold: and thoſe that will not fall down to worſhip the Image that they have made, they rage, and ſwell in Anger, and Wrath, and Revenge: And now that the Lord doth diſcover their deceits to us, and let us ſee them to be as Bell and the Dragon was, ſwallowing up all upon their luſts, and are never ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſeeking altogether after the honor of the world, and not after that which is of God; who ſeek ours, and not us: But by the Lord, we being awaked out of the ſleep of carnality, are as one an hungred, who found no life to our ſouls by their imaginary, fleſhly fancies, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurations, who raiſed death out of death, dead Reaſons, dead Uſes, dead Motives, dead Tryalls.</p>
            <p>And now that they come to the touchſtone, they will not abide, and we were left naked, and empty by them, wounded, and half-dead, and the Lord of his bountifull goodneſs holds out his free love to our ſouls: and having got a taſte of it, we are as little Children, ever hungring and thirſting for more, taſting of the Eternal love of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; being born again, nothing will ſatisfie our hungry ſouls, but the good milk of the Eternal living word of God, which is ſweeter to our taſte then the Hony-Comb, and we are brought to wait upon the Beloved of our Souls, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to take us with him into his garden of pure teachings, and doctrine of life; he ſpeaks good things to our ſouls, and his word is living and powerfull; every word that he ſpeaketh into our Souls, is the word of eternal life, and they kill the old nature in us, and worketh a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and gives life to our poor Souls, and raiſeth them out of the duſt of the Earth, to praiſe and glorifie his great and glorious name, and we have ſo much light let into our Souls from the Divine power of God, that it lets us ſee the deceits of all our proud Prieſts, and blind Guides, that their ſins teſtifie againſt them to their faces,<note place="margin">Hoſea. 5.5, 6, 7.</note> that they are a ſeed of evil doers, and live in the luſt <hi>and filth of the fleſh,</hi> Perſecuting, Killing, and Slaying the righteous and innocent ones, and drive them away from them by their Envious, Malicious, wicked practiſes in life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and are evil Examples; they are kings of Pride, and that is one of the ſeven Abominations which the Lords Soul loatheth.<note place="margin">Prov. 6.16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.16, 17, 18. And we are bound in Conſcience to teſtifie againſt it, and proud Prieſts are exceeding raging mad, and would not that we ſhould ſee beyond their Dirty Miry Doctrine of earthly conceivings and Imaginations, wherein
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166593:4"/>
they did deceive us, and have got our mony a long time for that which is no bread, and cauſed us to ſpend our labor for that which gave us no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to our ſouls, they were as theeves that wounded us, and left us; they led us into Pride by their evil example, ſeeing them live in Pride, we ſaying that if it was not right, they would not do it; and if they did it, we might do it; and ſo they being blind Guides, led us into blindneſs, and wounded our conſciences, and then they made us this cover for Pride, and ſaid, it was but decency; here they added their own inventions, and we knew it not, ſo long as we lived in <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Sodom</hi> with them, following the cuſtoms, and faſhions of the world, which we find now we are taught to deny; for the faſhion of the world paſſeth away, but the plagues of God is their portion: Wo to all deceivers: But we find our teacher (the Lord) writing his Law in our hearts, and teaching us by his Spirit,<note place="margin">Jer. 31.33, 34. Heb. 8.10, 11.</note> according to his promiſes made in the time of old. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33, 34. Heb. 8.10, 11. And he having eſtabliſhed his law in our hearts, ſheweth us ſin and evil; for we had not known that luſt had been a ſin, but that the pure Law of God ſaid, thou ſhalt not luſt, neither after Pride, nor Covetouſneſs, nor Envy, nor anger, nor pleaſures, nor the love of the world, nor the honor of the world, nor pleaſures, nor delights, becauſe the Prieſts that ſaid they were ſent of God, lived in all theſe things, and if they had been contrary to the mind, and will of God, they ſaying that they knew it, and ſpoke his words from his mouth, and we concluding within our ſelves, ſaid, If they may do it, we may do it; and ſo they deſtroyed us for lack of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and drove us from the Lord; but now he is gathering us to himſelf by his Spirit, according to his promiſe. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.11, 12, 13, 14, 15.<note place="margin">Ezek. 34.11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> And lets us ſee whither we were driven, even into the broad way of fleſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, but that the Lord of his infinite love hath diſcovered it to us, and we are brought to ſee where they left us, in the cloudy and dark day, and would never come to ſhew us any light, nor to ſet our feet into the way of peace, but led us further into the wilderneſs, out of Pride into Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo cauſed us to taſte of the forbidden fruit, ſaying, that Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was but a provident care, but we now find that it was the Devils Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine that they taught us: For the Lord ſaith to us by his Spirit, that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs is Idolatry, and draweth the heart from him; but theſe Covetous, Idolatrous Prieſts, run with greedineſs altogether after it, as thoſe greedy dumb dogs did, that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was ſent to cry out againſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11. He ſaid that the watchmen were al blind, as theſe proud Prieſts are now blinded with covetouſneſs; For Tythes, Gifts, and rewards hath blinded their eyes, that they ſee not Pride and Covetouſneſs to be a ſin, but greedie after it, Coveting altogether after great means, and if they have not to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their luſts, to live in pomp and pleaſures, they complain of the people: and if any for conſcience ſake towards God, ſeeing his Miniſtry to be free, and no ſale ſet upon it, which Miniſtry teacheth them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, as Pride, Covetouſneſs, the love of the world, knowing that if any man love the world, the love of the father is not in him, and that all that is in the world, as the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the Pride of life, is not of God, but is of the world, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake towards God, who is the father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166593:5"/>
wiſdom is not to be bought nor ſold.<note place="margin">Job 28.</note> 
               <hi>Job</hi> 28. and the Lords free love running forth to his People; ſaying, <hi>Why do you ſpend your mony for that which is no bread, and your labour for that which doth not ſatisfie? Hearken ye diligently to me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1, 2, 3, 4. Deut. 4.1, 2. Prov. 30.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>and eat ye that which is good, and let your ſouls delight themſelves in fatneſs, Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2, 3, 4. And we find it made good to our ſouls; and every word of God being pure, and a ſhield to them that truſt in it, and he that adds to it, or takes from it is to be reproved, being found a lyar. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.5, 6. And he that adds his own Inventions, the Lord is againſt him. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. And we that are of God are againſt him, and are bound to teſtifie againſt his deceits, and deceiveableneſs, according to the command of the Lord, who ſaith, have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkneſs,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.11. Joh. 10.1, 8, 10. <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               </note> but rather reprove them; and how can we ſee a thief, and conſent unto him, but we ſhal be guilty of the ſame crime? I pray you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, you that are ſpirituall, judge what I ſay: Are not all the Prieſts in <hi>England</hi> thieves? Anſwer for them, who wil; Do they not ſtudy for what they ſay, and walk by other lines? Did ever the Miniſters of Chriſt ſo? As he bade them <hi>take no thought what they ſhould eat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30. Luke 12.11, 12. Gal. 1.10, 11, 12, 15, 16. 2 Cor. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>nor what they ſhould drink, Luk.</hi> 12.22, 23. <hi>So he bade them take no thought what they ſhould ſay, for it ſhould be given them in that hour, Luke</hi> 12.11, 12. But theſe dare neither truſt God for their meat, nor drink, nor cloathing, as they did; nor for words to ſpeak, as they did, who were unlearned men, but as they were taught of God, and were made Miniſters, not by the will of man, but by the will of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11, 12. And were able Miniſters of the Spirit, and not of the Letter, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. But theſe both ſtudie what they ſhall eat, and what they ſhall drink, and what they ſhall put on, to make them proud, and what they ſhall do to oppreſs poor people, and they ſtudy every way how they may make their Miniſtery burdenſome, and ſtudie what to ſpeak, ſtudying old Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, and ſome of them writing down that which they ſpeak in papers: See if theſe do not diſtruſt God,<note place="margin">Jer. 23.29, 30, 31, 32. 2 Joh. 9.</note> and do diſhonor him, and are no Miniſters of the Spirit, but are Unbelievers, and Infidels, who diſtruſt God, and ſteal the words of their neighbours, as the falſe Prophets did. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29, 30, 31. But the Lord is againſt them now, as he was then, and ſends to cry out againſt them now as he did then; and when any is ſent by the Lord, to cry out againſt them now, to tell them of their deceits, and deceivableneſs,<note place="margin">Acts 7.47, 48, 49. Ver. 57, 58, 59. Acts 6.11, 12, 13. Mat. 23.27, 28, 29, 30, 31.</note> and how that they are no Miniſters of Chriſt, who do not abide in his Doctrine, but teach for Doctrine the traditions of men, and call a ſtone-houſe a Church, and ſay that God dwelleth there, and when any is ſent by the Lord to cry out againſt them there, as <hi>Steven</hi> did, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. who ſaid, God that made the world did not dwell in Temples made with hands, and that evil generation of the uncircumciſed in hearts and ears did murder poor <hi>Steven,</hi> the Servant of the Lord, and ſaid he was a blaſphemer, and came to overturn the Law, and the Statutes that were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth by <hi>Moſes;</hi> and ſo theſe perſecuting Prieſts here in <hi>Yorkſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, their ſins teſtifie againſt them to their face, that they are of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that ſlew the righteous blood, and they would have all to take notice that they know not God; for when any is ſent to them, and ſays that God doth not dwell in any of thoſe Idol Temples that are made with hands, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24.<note place="margin">Acts 17.25.</note> neither is he worſhipped there by Traditions, Cuſtoms,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166593:5"/>
and Rudiments of the world with mens hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.25. But he is <hi>a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 4.23, 24. 1 Pet. 2.5. 1 Cor. 3.19. 2 Cor. 6.16. Iſa. 54.11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>for he ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him, Joh.</hi> 4.23, 24. And that the Church of Chriſt is made all of <hi>living ſtones,</hi> elect and precious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. and that the Saints are made the Temples of the <hi>living God,</hi> as the Corinthians did witneſs, and that they ſhall need no man to teach them, for the Lord is the teacher of his himſelf alone by his Spirit, and asks them how they came to their Miniſtry, and bids them prove what they have ſaid, they run away, and will not ſtand to prove their call to the Miniſtry, but lets them be beaten, and ſtruck by the uncircumciſed in hearts, and ears; for none that are cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed by the ſpirit of the living God cometh there, to ſtand up to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people. <hi>But the hireling fleeth, becauſe he is an hireling,</hi> that the Scriptures may be fulfilled, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.12, 13. <hi>And the thief cometh not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 10.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>but for to kill, and to ſteal, and to deſtroy. Joh.</hi> 10.10. <hi>But the good ſhepherd, he layeth down his life for the ſheep,</hi> but theſe that cannot prove their call to the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, the Miniſtration of the Spirit, which excells that of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> they having nothing but what they have ſtolne, and ſtudied for; Their old Author ſtudied ſpirit fails them, and the <hi>hireling fleeth</hi> becauſe he is an <hi>hireling,</hi> and not the true Shepherd, and the thief kills, ſteals, and deſtroyes, and ſaith to the people, hear him not whom God hath ſent, take him Officers, and put him in the ſtocks, and let him be had to Priſon, and ſo turns Perſecutor; and you all know that Perſecution is of the Devil; and now thoſe diveliſh Prieſts ſhew themſelves what they are now that they are come to be tried, but it is but that they may be made manifeſt what generation they are of; and when they cannot defend themſelves by their old Author-ſtudied Spirit, it failing them, then they Petition to the outward powers of the Land, that they may more plainly appear; but the Foxes are ſo ſubtile, that they twine about into the hole of their earthly wiſdom in their Petition, that they would cover over them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as if they were the Miniſters of Chriſt, and would juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but God will condemn them; <hi>And it were better for them that a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone were hanged about their necks,</hi> and they themſelves caſt into the Sea, then that they ſhould offend one of theſe little ones that believeth in the Lord; the Petitioners are many of them Perſecutors, and I do not queſtion but that both Parliament, and Army, and all that fear the Lord, and are acquainted with his teachings, the teachings of the Spirit of Grace in the leaſt meaſure, thoſe that know it, know that it teacheth to deny all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs, as it is made manifeſt by the Divine light of God within, where the light of God doth ſhine in the hearts of any, as it doth in thoſe who are taught of God, who have the heavenly treaſure in <hi>earthly veſſels,</hi> as the Saints had. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7. And thoſe that are enlightned and guided by the ſame Spirit that they were, which ſpirit is but one, where it is made manifeſt: I ſay, all thoſe that know this ſpiritual teaching of Jeſus Chriſt, both Parliament, and Army, and all others, know that this bleſſed Spirit teacheth to deny perſecution, and worketh out anger, and envy, and wrath, and revenge, purging out the old nature, working into love, and bowells of Compaſſion, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Meekneſs, Temperance, Patience, Godlineſs, and brotherly kindneſs, which cauſeth the old man
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166593:6"/>
to be put off, and the old perſecuting nature, and cauſeth the new man to be put on, and withall to be made partaker of the Divine nature; and thoſe that know this in part, will ſee that thoſe falſe Prieſts have a filthy deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart, and will be diſcovered, and made manifeſt in their deceivable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by thoſe that have the Spirit of God, and they have an end to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for to have the praiſe of men, as the <hi>Scribes</hi> had that ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat, as theſe do, proud <hi>Phariſees,</hi> they will appear to be fair outſides, but they have inſides full of rottenneſs and deceitfulneſs of heart, but you know what is the portion of ſuch:<note place="margin">Mat. 23.1, 2, 27, 28, 29.</note> See <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. And it will not be unknown to the Heads, and Rulers of the Nation, what ſort of men they were that took counſel together, to take Jeſus by ſubtilty to kill him. And then they may ſee what Generation theſe are of, and what ſeed after the fleſh, but not after the Spirit; for they that are after the fleſh, they preſecute them that are after the Spirit; You heads and Rulers of the people, ſee that you ſtand in the Counſel of the Lord, and mind that which is of God in you; that is pure which ſheweth you the vanity of your minds, and checks you when you do contrary to it, and it will guide your minds towards God, who is pure, and cauſe you to ſtand in his pure fear, which will lead you into the true wiſdom of God, to govern the people in righteouſneſs, and to take away that unrighteous Law, or Statute made by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> which the Prieſts, your Petitioners, make their refuge, to perſecute and Impriſon the Righteous by, and deny the Law of God, or practiſe of the Saints, the people of God in former ages, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. When any thing was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to him that ſate by, the firſt was to hold his peace, and the other was to ſpeak, and all might ſpeak one by one, that all might be edified; let that of <hi>Mary</hi> be put forth, and put in one in order to this, which was the practiſe of the Church of God, that the deceivers may be laid open, and made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt what they are; Act in righteouſneſs, that you may receive the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; Take heed of holding up that which God is throwing down, now he is making his power known, caſting down the mighty out of their Thrones, and bringing down the haughtineſs of men, throwing down every high thought, and every high Imagination: Let ſuch Laws be eſtabliſhed as tend to the puniſhment of evil doers, and countenancing thoſe that do well, and then you will ſee the Foxes, and falſe Prieſts, will be found out; Let truth be declared freely by any one where it is made manifeſt; Who art thou that wouldſt limit the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by thy carnal mind? What ever thou art, God will limit thee, and throw thee down out of thy Throne, be what thou wilt; But thou that loveſt the truth, and ſtandeſt up for it, as it is in Jeſus, thou ſhalt be Crowned with Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Is it according either to Conſcience, or the Law of Equity and reaſon, that theeves ſhould make their prey of the Righteous? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, and lay it to heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it according to Equity, or the truth of God, that any mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhould be kept under a beaſtly, corrupt mans will, that ſwells in anger, and if any go to eaſe his burdned Conſcience, to be beaten, and ſet in the ſtocks, and ſtoned in the ſtreets; is this according to the practiſe of the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt? Let the Scriptures be your Rule, and the Lord your judge, and be not upholders of thoſe deceivers; for God will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor himſelf in throwing of them down.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:166593:6"/>3. Is it according to the righteous Law of God, or mans corrupt will, that the righteous ſhould ſuffer, and the wicked go free, and eſcape by lies and flatteries? let every thing be brought to light, and let the tranſgreſſors be puniſhed, and the Innocent cleared; For God will be honored, and he will not always ſtrive, he will reprove even Kings for his righteous chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens ſake, and he will take away the reproach of his people himſelf, and no deceitfull perſon ſhall dwell in his houſe; God is a Spirit, and none knows him but ſuch as are ſpiritual, and born again, and the righteous they ſuffer, and no man layeth it to heart, but God is judge himſelf, and he will be avenged of all his Enemies.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is there are reaſon that we ſhould pay, or be compelled to pay for that which we have not? is not this unrighteous? They ſay they are Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and we do ask them what Scripture they have for their Rule to take tythe Hay, or Corn, tythe Lamb, and Wooll, tythe Eggs, and money for Reak paſſing up our Chimnies, and money for Mares, and Foals, and Kine, and Calves, and tythe Apples, and Cherries; and to have an end of all our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, we would have them to give account of their Miniſtry, and how they came to be made Miniſters of the Spirit, and what Scripture they have for their Rule to take tythes, and whether it were ever the practiſe of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, yea or no? who laboured with their hands, and deſired rather to dye, then to make the Goſpel burdenſom, that they might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to all that come after; and they walking contrary to Chriſt and his Apoſtles, have loſt their examples, and make the Parliament their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſword, and carnal bulwark for the account of their Miniſtry, or ground of their Doctrine, and ſay, the Parliament do allow them, and can no ways clear themſelves by Scripture, and we finding the Miniſtry of Chriſt to be a free Miniſtry, and the Goſpel not to be burdenſom, though they clear themſelves to be the Miniſters of man and not of God; the Apoſtle was a Miniſter, not made by the will of man, but by the will of God: and theſe walking contrary to the Miniſters of Chriſt, and contrary to the Scriptures, and we never profited by them, they ſtarved our ſouls by their cold, dark, and barren Miniſtry of their own Inventions, and they ſay that we would juſtle God out of his Throne, but it is but the God of the World, <hi>Mammon,</hi> which they ſo much thirſt after; for it is the deſire of our ſouls to ſee the onely true God to ſit upon his Throne, ruling by his power, and every Spirit, and as the Lord is large in his love to us, though they call us Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Quakers, or what Nick-name they can invent, and every way ſeek to caſt dirt upon the pure Truth, ſtanding in oppoſition againſt the power of truth, in any where it is made manifeſt, as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> did, but their folly ſhall appear to all men, as theirs did; but we cannot in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience pay for that old rotten ſtuffe, which runs out of their old bottels, old corrupt natures, which poureth forth nothing but corruption, and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as Railings, and Revilings, and curſed ſpeakings, ſpeaking evil of that which they know not, and becauſe we cannot buy of their old ſtinking wares, as we did formerly, not queſtioning them, took them for good upon their words, but now the Fountain of their ſtinking puddle is made known, and the Lord teacheth us better things, we are ever bound to praiſe his name, and we receive of his Love, and ſpiritual teachings, freely receiving,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166593:7"/>
and Grace for Grace, growing up from Grace to Grace, in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and as we have received freely, we are made to hold it forth freely to others again, not ſeeking our ſelves, as they do, but ſeeking the good, and welfare of one anothers Souls, by the power of the Lord, as it ruleth in us, running forth to ſeek the good of all, and we cannot hold them up in their deceits, and we cannot pay for that which we have not, neither did we ever receive any ſpiritual food, or refreſhings from them; we teſtifie againſt them, as it is our bounden duty to let our light ſhine forth to others, and though the proud Prieſts, as in all that which they do, it is for money, which is their <hi>Diana,</hi> and all that which they look after; They do not ſeek us, but ours; And as we receive of the Lord freely, we cannot but declare, though they threaten, and do ſue, and go to Law for carnal maintenance, which both Jeſus Chriſt and his true Miniſters do forbid, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.40. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. but they do not abide in his Doctrine, as is now made plain in our book of <hi>Eaſter Reckonings:</hi> And we would reckon with them, as we have there declared about the pure Doctrine, by the Spirit of the Lord made known, and taught to us; And if they could prove themſelves warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably by Scriptures to have Rule from them, which we own the Life of, and make it appear to us to be Miniſters of the Spirit, they ſhould have their due, and if they will lay open their ſhamefull dealings to all men, let all take notice of their folly, that God may have the praiſe, who hath laid open their deceits, and taught us freely by his holy Spirit in theſe our dayes; to him be all holy praiſe, both now and for evermore, who is worthy to be praiſed, God bleſſed for ever.</p>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Would have thee to peruſe this enſuing Treatiſe, or ſomething in Anſwer to the Counties Petition put up to the Parliament by the Prieſts, and many of their aſſociates here in York-ſhire, wherein their flatteries, and ſubtilties, and deceits are diſcovered and laid open; and although theybe ſo cunning, that in their Petition they have kept out themſelves, and put it up in the name of the People; yet they were the chiefeſt Actors, and got all as many as they could, Boyes, and Girles in ſeveral places, that knew not their left hand from their right, to ſet their hands to their Petition, and many people that had any knowledge of God in the leaſt meaſure, denied to joyn with them; But read it over, and it will to thee their deceits more plainly manifeſt, and fully diſcover.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Rich. Farnworth.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="petitions">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:166593:7"/>
            <head>The Counties Petition.</head>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>To the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe humble Petition of many inhabitants of the County of</hi> York, <hi>and City of</hi> York, <hi>and County of the ſame City, Humbly ſheweth, That your Petitioners, who are leſs then the leaſt of the Mercies they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, as they deſire to be ſenſible of that good decree of peace and truth which through the good hand of God upon your Counſels and Indeavours, they partake of, and are therefore Petitioners to the Lord for you, that he would remember you for good, and ſpare you according to the Multitude of his mercies, and ſo withall they think it their duty humbly to preſent unto you, the deep ſenſe they have of ſome evils and dangers which they apprehend very nearly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the truth of God, and Goſpel of Salvation, or the proſperous courſe thereof, whereon the glory of peace, and ſafety of this Nation, beſides the eternal welfare of precious ſouls (more worth then worlds) do much depend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That many ſcandalous and ignorant Perſons, Enemies to the People, and ways of God, upholders and practiſers of the aboliſhed Ceremonies, and no friends to the preſent Government, and peace of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, are continued in the work of the Miniſtry, to the prejudice of that calling, the hinderance of Reformation, and danger of Immortal Souls.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt by whom we have believed, whoſe labors have been ſo profitable, and yet ſo neceſſary to the Church of God, and whoſe reputations and incouragement ought to be ſo dear unto us, are daily loaden with contempt and reproach, diſturbed in the diligent and peaceable execution of their office, by evil and unreaſonable men, and alſo undermined in their calling and maintenance, whereby the courſe of the Goſpel is much hindred; and the Spirit of Gods people, nay, we doubt not to ſay the Spirit of God himſelf grieved and vexed, the precious Ordinances of Chriſt trodden under foot, and conſequently the welfare of this toſſed, diſtracted common-wealth very much endangered; For if the juſt Lord, who is in the midſt of us, ſpared not his ancient people, the Tribes of his inheritance, when once they began to mock his Meſſengers, and deal injuriouſly with thoſe that are ſent to preach the glad tidings of the Goſpel, whereby they filled up the meaſure of their ſins, and brought upon themſelves wrath without remedy, even wrath to the utmoſt; and we ſee no reaſon why the unchangeable God ſhould not proceed by the ſame meaſure againſt gentile Churches, as of ſuch you have had alſo nearer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166593:8"/>
in the fall of thoſe perſons whom the Lord caſt out before you, the rock of whoſe ruine was their oppoſition to a Godly and conſcientious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> They take boldneſs to repreſent, that the liberty granted by the Parliament in matters of Religion, and the worſhip of God, is very much abuſed, to the increaſe of Popery, and prophaneſs, contrary to your inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the ſame: Your Petitioners ſeriouſly conſidering, and laying to heart theſe things, think it their further duty, earneſtly to beſeech you by the glorious, and fearfull name of God, which is every day blaſphemed, by the precious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, which is much diſhonored, and deſpiſed, and by whatſoever is dear unto us, which by theſe and ſuch like evils we believe to be much endangered, That you would take theſe particulars into ſerious and ſpeedy conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That you would take a more effectual courſe for removing of ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and unworthy Miniſters from the office and work of the Miniſtry, then yet is, or can be taken by the Committee for plundred Miniſters ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at Weſtminſter, in regard of the great diſtance of this County, that ſo the Parliament may not be charged, not ſo much as by neglect, to build again thoſe things they have deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That you would ſpeak comfortably to thoſe that teach the good knowledge of the Lord, ſeeing that God himſelf hath given (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding manifold infirmities) teſtimonial ſeals to many of them, and take care that they may have a comfortable ſubſiſtance, that you would ſupport the honor and reverence of the Univerſities, neceſſary to the ſupply of able Miniſters, and bear witneſs againſt thoſe who daily diſcover their enmity to the Office and Ordinances of the Goſpel, whereby life will be given to your well eſtabliſhed Laws, and inferior Magiſtrates encouraged to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and further the Goſpel in their ſeveral ſtations, and much danger of the Common-wealth prevented, which cannot but be feared; For the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſers of the Miniſtry, whoſe Principles are full of confuſion, and lead to caſting off the Rulings as well as the teachings of men, wherewith they have given much cauſe of ſuſpition in this, and full evidence in other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly.</hi> That you would take care to build ſuch battlements about your grants of liberty, in matters of Religion, that Popiſh and prophane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may not take advantage thereby, to diſhonor God, deſpiſe his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, pollute his Sabboths, and ſo the land be filled with Atheiſm, Ignorance, and Idolatry.</p>
               <p>So ſhall the Lord, who hitherto hath been a wall of fire round about us, be alſo for glory in the midſt amongſt us, and your Petitioners be further engaged to pray for a bleſſing upon your Counſells, and perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:166593:8"/>
               <head>To the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe humble Petition of many Inhabitants of the County of York,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petition.</note> 
                  <hi>the City of York, and County of the ſame City, humbly ſheweth, that your Petitioners, who are leſs then the leaſt of the mercies they enjoy, as they deſire to be ſenſible of that good decree of peace, and truth, which through the good hand of God upon your counſels, and endeavours they partake of, and are therefore Petitioners to the Lord for you, that he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you for good, and ſpare you according to the multitude of his mercies: and ſo withall they think it their duty humbly to preſent unto you, the deep ſenſe they have of ſome evils and dangers which they apprehend very nearly to concern the truth of God, and Goſpel of Salvation, for the proſperous courſe thereof, whereon the glory of peace, and ſafety of this Nation, beſides the eternal well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of precious ſouls, more worth then worlds, do much depend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Petitioners are full of flatteries, and ſubtilty,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and ſhew themſelves to be carnal, that run from the Lord to take counſell of men (for that which they call ſpiritual) that ſit to judge of temporal affairs; and it ſhews that the Prieſts of the world are the Miniſters of man, and not of God, and dare not truſt him, nor take his counſail, neither have they the ſword of the Spirit, as the true Miniſters had; their weapons were not carnal, but ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and mighty through God, to throw down ſtrong holds, and they were made through him that loved them, more then Conquerors, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note> But theſe ſhew themſelves to be carnal, and ignorant of the ſame power that ruled in them, that run to outward power to uphold them, as the Jews, and Scribes, and Phariſees did, that ſought for the honor of the world, and the praiſe of men as theſe do, and were enemies to Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Joh. 5.42, 43, 44.</note> as theſe are: For were theſe Petitioners acquainted with what they do profeſs, it would draw their minds up to the Lord, who is the mighty Counſellor, the everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9. to direct their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to him, and not to run without, to take Counſell of men,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 9. Iſaiah 30.</note> who ſit to judge of temporal things, to ask Counſel about ſpiritual, and ſo run from the Lord, the mighty Counſellor, and the judge of the whole Earth, who doth direct all thoſe that truſt in him to take his Counſell, both for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, and ſpirituals, and threatneth woe to them that take Counſel, but not of him; and the woe is to the diſobedient Children, that go down into <hi>Egypt</hi> for help, to make fleſh their Arm, who do not truſt in the living God, but are haters of him, though in their words to him they do profeſs love, but by their actions they deny him, and are to every good work abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, and Reprobate, <hi>Titus</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Profeſſing they know God,<note place="margin">Titus 1.16.</note> and hate thoſe that are known of him, as by their fruits it doth appear; for they do both Perſecute, Envy, Backbite, and are exceeding Proud, and Covetous, and Oppreſs, grinding the faces of the poor,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.8.</note> and it is not unknown what fruits thoſe are; it cannot be denied, but that they are fruits of the fleſh; they that are in the fleſh, cannot pleaſe God; Was it not the great men of the World that did make their ſuite ſo much to the Councel of State, or thoſe that ſate to judge the People amongſt the Jews, who were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to Jeſus Chriſt? as <hi>Paul</hi> was accuſed for a Blaſphemer, &amp; an Heretick,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166593:9"/>
and was complained againſt, or petitioned for, by the Scribes and Phariſees, and Elders of the people, to the high Prieſt that ſat in the ſeat of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to have had his life taken away, and ſaid, he was a ſeditious fellow: and <hi>Steven,</hi> they ſaid he was a blaſphemer, and they not being able to reſiſt the wiſdom,<note place="margin">Acts 6.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> and the ſpirit by which he ſpoke: <hi>Acts</hi> 6.10, 11, 12. then they ſuborned men, ſtirred up the People to ſwear falſly againſt him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Councel, and ſaid that they heard him ſpeak blaſphemous things againſt <hi>Moſes;</hi> the Temple, and the Law, when he went to declare the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that the Lord ſent him withall; As he doth now ſend many to cry out againſt the deceits of the Prieſts, and they not being able to defend themſelves by Scripture, nor warrant from God, they ſtir up the ſuborned men, and rude multitude, who are utter enemies to God, and the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, to Petition againſt thoſe, to whom the Lord hath manifeſted his love, and made his power known in ſome meaſure, to praiſe and glorifie his great and glorious name; and thoſe Petitioners are as thoſe were that cried to the high Prieſt, let us have <hi>Barrabas,</hi> who was a murderer, ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and Chriſt Crucified, in whom was found no guile, but becauſe he came to teſtifie againſt their deceits, yet they ſaid, he was a deceiver, and a blaſphemer: they that were Petitioners againſt the ttuth of God in that Generation, went under the ſame colour, and pretence then, that theſe do now, Petitioning againſt Seditious fellows that came to overturn their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, Laws, and Cuſtoms; and the Scribes, Phariſees, and Elders of the people cryed out againſt them for Blaſphemy, and Hereſie; Nay, they ſpared not to call the good man of the houſe <hi>Belzebub,</hi> and ſaid he was the Prince of Devils; and <hi>Paul,</hi> they ſayd he was a Ring leader of that Sect; and the Silver-ſhrine-makers, becauſe hey ſaw that he came to overturn their <hi>Diana,</hi> which brought them ſo much gain, they ſaid, that if they did let him alone, all men would be drawn after him, and they ſhould be in danger to ſuffer the loſs of all, not onely their handicraft would be ſet at naught, but their Goddeſs <hi>Dianah</hi> would be overthrown, and then the ſenſe and conſideration of that ſeiſed deep upon them, whereupon they went, and ſtirred up all the people againſt the Servants of the Lord, to have ſlaughtered them for teſtifying the truth that ſtruck at their deceits, and ſtirred up all the whole City, ſetting them on an uproar, many not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they did, but as they were led on by the on-ſetters to miſchief, and cried with a loud voice, great is <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> and if it be but rightly conſidered now, it will be found out that theſe Petitioners here in York-ſhire are of the ſame Generation, and the Prieſts being with the Scribes and Phariſees, and Leaders of the Petitioners, ſtruck into a deep ſenſe that they have of the loſs of their great Goddeſs <hi>Diana,</hi> their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way of worſhip, and beaſtly wares, that they have had ſuch ſale for, ſhall now come down, and they loſe all their gain, and none will buy their wares any longer, that comes to taſt of better, that the ſenſe of this doth ſtrike deeply at them, and lye heavy upon them, and the ſenſe of no other evil and danger; that is the greateſt, and it is time for the beaſt to colour over himſelf neatly, and Petition now, and cry, help Magiſtrate now, or all is gone, we cannot defend our ſelves any way elſe, and if you fail us now, we are utterly undone for ever, we canot defend our ſelves by Scripture, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166593:9"/>
our converſation teſtifies againſt us, that we neither follow the example of Jeſus Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, who were his true Miniſters, and the People they begin to ſee it; and truth it is, we have no right to take tythes, nor to have hire, we cannot juſtifie our actions any wayes by Scripture, and if you ſtand not to us now, we loſe all, and ſhall be utterly undone, and ruinated for ever. And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They think it their humble duty to preſent unto you the deep ſenſe they have of ſome evils and dangers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petition.</note> 
                  <hi>which they apprehend very nearly to concern the truth of God, and Goſpel of Salvation, or the proſperous courſe thereof, whereon the glory of peace, and ſafety of this Nation, beſides the eternal welfare of precious ſouls, (more worth then worlds) doth depend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Conſider of it, If theſe Petitioners be not of the ſame Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of evil doers that the Scribes and Phariſees were, that laboured ſo much and Petitioned, or falſly accuſed the Son of God, Jeſus Chriſt and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and followers to the Counſel of the people Aſſembled together, time after time, to have deſtroyed not onely them in whom the truth was declared, but laboured every way to have deſtroyed the truth it ſelf, but could not, for the more that they were perſecuted, they more did grow; and as it was then, ſo is it now.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But the ſubtilty of the Serpent that ruled in the Jews chief Prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſees then, ruleth in theſe Petitioners now in this age, as by their fruits it doth appear.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When the Lord ſent forth his meſſengers then to declare his truth, they ſtrucke them, and put them in the ſtocks, and ſtoned, and railed, and hated, and ſhamefully intreated them, and when they were not able to reſiſt the wiſdom, and the ſpirit by which they ſpake, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 6. then ſome of them they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, as <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> and ſtoned <hi>Steven,</hi> and ſought falſe witneſs againſt him to put him to death, and ſought to the counſell to have the life of them, all ſuch blood-ſuckers they were; yet it was under a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, or cloak, or pretence of godlineſs, and ſtirred up the people, telling them that they were ſeditious fellows, as <hi>Steven</hi> was, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. and men that came to overturn the Law, and the Statutes given forth by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and came to ſpeak blaſphemous things againſt the Temple, and under that colour of Schiſmaticks, and Hereticks, Sedition, and Blaſphemy, did the pure truth ſuffer; and this is the ſame generation by which it doth ſuffer now; and let but theſe wicked Prieſts have but their corrupt wills fulfilled, and they would murder all, in whom any thing of God was made manifeſt, under colour or pretence of Papiſts, or prophane Perſons, when as they are themſelves the wickedſt profane perſons of all others, and ſtir up many to be their Executioners to miſchief, that know not the right hand from the left in point of Religion, in ſtrike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtoning, and falſly accuſing the good Converſation of the righteous, and ſhamefully entreating them, and Petitioning againſt them: But,</p>
               <p>Fourthly, They may juſtly expect the juſt hand of God upon them, and the plagues of God to be poured forth upon them for their exceeding great wickedneſs; for they are the peace-breakers of the Commonwealth, not of <hi>England</hi> onely, but of Iſrael alſo, as much as in them lies.</p>
               <p>And they may be ſenſible of it, they may ſee themſelves enemies both to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166593:10"/>
the Goſpel of Salvation, and the proſperous courſe thereof, every ways hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the truth from being declared,<note place="margin">Ezek. 34.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Hoſea 6.9.</note> as much as in them lies, to the utmoſt of their power, deceivers, or deſtroyers of ſouls, which is more worth then worlds; <hi>And as a troop of robbers wait for a man, ſo the company of Prieſts murder in the way by conſent:</hi> as it is now by their fruits made manifeſt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Therefore O ye ſhepherds, hear the word of the Lord; Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſhepherds, and I will require my flock at their hands, and cauſe them to ceaſe from feeding the flock, neither ſhall they feed themſelves any more; for I will deliver my flock from them, that they may not be meat for them,</hi> Ezek. 34.8, 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 34.9, 10.</note>Fifthly, <hi>Shall you not be viſited for theſe things ſaith the Lord? Let the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked joyn hand in hand, yet they ſhall not go unpuniſhed; for ſaith the Lord, I will be avenged of all mine enemies; vengeance is mine, and I will repay; Woe to the wicked, It ſhall go ill with them, both Prieſts, and people, for the leaders of them cauſe them to erre.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.16. Hoſea. 4.9.</note> Iſa. 9.16. <hi>There is like Prieſt, like people,</hi> Hoſ. 4.9. All joyn together to perſecute the truth, and to hinder the free courſe of the Goſpel, and to break the peace of the Commonwealth, and as much as in them lies, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſouls of the righteous, now that the Lord is ſending forth his ſervants to cry out againſt the deceits of the world, and the worſhip of the beaſt, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the works of their own hands, traditions, and rudiments of the world, which are not after God,<note place="margin">Col. 2.20, 21, 22.</note> but by the will of man, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20, 21, 22. and mens corrupt wills being croſt, and the deceits of the Prieſts here in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> being diſcovered, and the Lord ſending to them, to teſtifie it to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they will not ſtand to prove themſelves neither to be Miniſters of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor of the ſpirit, but run away, and cauſe that thoſe whom the Lord ſendeth to them, be beaten, and abuſed, and given up into the hands of the rude multitude, which is contrary both to the practiſe of Chriſt, and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; they never ſtruck, nor cauſe any to be ſtruck, but on the contrary, received ſtripes; <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were beaten, and put in the priſon, See <hi>Act.</hi> 5.26,<note place="margin">Acts 5.26, 27, 28, &amp;c.</note> 27, 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and threatned they ſhould ſpeak no more in the name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. And,</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Theſe Prieſts bear teſtimony to the ſame deeds here in <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> for many have been beaten for declaring the truth as it is in Jeſus, and many ſtoned, that ſtones have flown as faſt as bullets in a battel, and the dogs have been ſet on by their hearers, and they themſelves having been in the ſtreets, and being ſpoken to, would not prove themſelves, but got away: Are not theſe the fruits of the Jews, who were enemies to Jeſus Chriſt? did not they ſtone <hi>Steven</hi> to death for witneſſing the truth? <hi>Act.</hi> 7.59, 60.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 7.59.</note>And had it not been the Lords power, more then their mercy at that time, their mercies being very cruelties, all had been deſtroyed: for they ſtoned a great ſpace out of the Town, and ſtones did hit on the backs and heads of the people, as if they had clattered on a wall, and none did ſeek to quench the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult; ſee whether theſe be fruits of Chriſts Miniſtery, or of Antichriſts? but it is but that the Scriptures may be fulfilled, and now it is fulfilling here in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and the Prieſts are the greateſt perſecutors: was not Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſtoned,<note place="margin">Joh. 10.31, 32, 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.31, 32, 33. and perſecuted by the high-Prieſts? and ſhall the ſervant be greater then the Lord? Did the Miniſters of Chriſt ever perſecute as the Miniſters of the world do, and eſpecially here in <hi>Yorkſhire?</hi> the Jews were perſecutors, who were enemies to Ieſus Chriſt, and ſtoned both
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166593:10"/>
him and his, and beat them, and ſtruck them. <hi>Paul</hi> received five times forty ſtripes, ſave one; they ſtruck Ieſus, and ſpit in his face, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.65, 66, 67.</note> And thoſe that ſtoned and ſtruck them, and did ſo ſhamefully entreat them, petitioned or falſly accuſed them to the Council, ſeveral times, to have had their lives; and they were willing to ſuffer death, rather then deny the truth: Ieſus himſelf witneſſed a good Confeſſion before <hi>Pilate,</hi> which Ieſus we are brought to confeſs before men, for whoſe ſake we are hated and perſecuted both by Prieſts and people here in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> who do profeſs him, as the Iews did, but will not confeſs or witneſs him ruling in them by his ſpirit, but do deny him in their actions, as their fruits make them manifeſt.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Would they ſtand the tryal, and prove themſelves before their people? then let them be laid open what they are, but they will not ſtand; are they not of a cowardly ſpirit? Such is the Univerſity Spirit, it is a thieviſh ſpirit, and will not, nor dare not ſtand, they not being able to reſiſt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in thoſe who are ſent to cry out againſt the deceits of them, as <hi>Steven</hi> and the reſt did; but theſe run away: and becauſe they have a Popiſh Law to flye to, they impriſon the ſervants of the Lord as many are here in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at <hi>York,</hi> and have been a long time in priſon by theſe perſecuting Prieſts here in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> and they will not that the truth ſhould come to light, nor they to be tryed by courſe of Law; ſee if theſe be not hinderers of the courſe of the Goſpel, and deſtroy the righteous, both ſoul and body, as much as in them lies, but that the Lords love doth more appear in their preſervation, then the Prieſts mercy in delivering; but woe is their portion, and they break the Peace of the Nation, not ſuffering the truth to be declared, after that they have done ſpeaking, but rather encourage the rude multitude to beat and ſtrike the ſervants of the living God, and raile and revile them, but wil not ſtand, but let the rude people break the peace of the Land; and that which they call their Church, is rather a ſlaughter-houſe; but the hireling fleeth becauſe he is an hireling, that the Scriptures may be fulfilled; and the thief comes not but to kill, and to ſteal, and to deſtroy, as it is now made manifeſt by their fruits, or the Prieſts actings here in <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> and then as the Iews did, they petition, or falſly accuſe the good converſation of the righteous, to the Councel of State, but they are made manifeſt whoſe ſervants they are, and the judgement will return upon their own pate: <hi>Woe to the Idol-ſhepherds:</hi> they are in a deep ſenſe of loſing their Trade, and Handicraft, whereby they have a long time decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the people, and now they cry out, Great is <hi>Diana,</hi> or the merchandiſe of <hi>Babylon,</hi> wherein we receive our gain, and if theſe men be letten alone, we ſhall loſe all our profits, but we will cry out againſt them, that we be not taken notice on our ſelves, who are the enemies, and hinderers of the Goſpel, which is the power of God unto ſalvation, and we want that power amongſt us, and thats the reaſon why our Miniſtery works no Reformation.</p>
               <p>And that they may not take notice of us,<note place="margin">A confeſſion for the Prieſts. An exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Prieſts.</note> we will begin at home to cut off all thoſe that are ſcandalous, but indeed we may ſay we cannot cleer our ſelves, for we were never ſent, but ran, and we have not profited the people at all, as it is now made manifeſt by our fruitleſs Miniſtery, for all is light and vain, covetous and prophane; therefore let me exhort you by the Lord to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with your own ſelves, and ſee that you do not run on further into wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166593:11"/>
now that you are made manifeſt, your ſins teſtifie to your face, that you are enemies of the truth of God, and he will bruiſe you with his Iron rod for deceiving poor ſouls ſo long, for the higheſt of you in your fleſhly wiſdom, is the higheſt deceiver, and the Lord is againſt you all, both great and ſmall, though you ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That many ſcandalous and ignorant perſons, enemies to the people and ways of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petition.</note> 
                  <hi>upholders and practizers of the aboliſhed Ceremonies, and no friends to the preſent Government and peace of this Commonwealth, are continued in the work of the Miniſtery, to the prejudice of that Calling, the hinderance of Reformation, and danger of Immortal ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>You may ſee how you have been deceived all this while, and lived under a Popiſh Miniſtery, and now that it is diſcovered, they would have people to take notice of it, that many of them are of the Popiſh Clergy, and are ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and enemies both to the ways of God, and the people of God; and if your underſtandings were enlightened, you may ſee that there is but little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of them;<note place="margin">2 Joh. 9. 1 Cor. 2.14.</note> for they are all contrary both to Chriſt and his true Miniſters, and he that abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. &amp; they are all carnal, in their firſt nature, and the natural man knows not the things of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned; and no man knows the Father but the Son, and he to whom he is revealed: The Heathen know not God, and all are Heathens that know him not, in their natural ſtate and condition; the world by wiſdom knows not God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.18, 19.20. Acts 17.20, 21, 22, 23, &amp;c.</note> but worſhips an unknown God; and thoſe that live in ignorance, and Papiſts, are all in one nature, and both worſhip an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known God, as the <hi>Athenians</hi> did; and every one in his natural ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion lives in darkneſs, Athieſm, Popery, and Idolatry, worſhipping the works of their own hands, and following the imaginations of their own hearts, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neer to God with their mouth and lips, but their hearts are far from him, as thoſe were that he complained of by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Iſa.</hi> 29.13.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Let me ask you that profeſs your ſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> but are not of the letter, for you will not let it be your rule to walk by, but run from it, and will not abide the tryal; but are you not all made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by your fruits, what you are? Take notice of it all people, conſider, and ſee how you have been deceived all this while; they will all be found deceivers, and blinde guides, that deceive the people: did God ever ſend ſcandalous and ignorant perſons, enemies to the people and ways of God, into the work of his Miniſtery? and do not your fruits declare that you were never ſent of him? who are enemies both to him, and his, where he is made manifeſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Do not your ſins teſtifie againſt you to your face, that you are none of his, the higheſt of you? are you not all unprofitable ſervants? do not you make the people light, and vain? as the falſe Prophets did, which ran, but the Lord never ſent them, as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Are you not proud? and pride is of the devil, and God doth forbid it, and ſaith it is an abomination to his ſoul, and that is contrary to God, and is ſcandalous; and ſhews that you are guided by the ſpirit of error, and are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the ſpirit of truth; that teacheth to deny pride, which is one of the ſeven abominations, which the woe is to: <hi>Woe to the Crown of pride;</hi> for the devil, he is the King of Pride, then woe to you, ye deviliſh proud-Prieſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:166593:11"/>Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Learn of me, I am meek and lowly in heart;</hi> but you ſhew that you are ignorant of his teachings, and are enemies to thoſe that are brought into the obedience of his teachings, which teacheth ſelf-denyal; and you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſelf-lovers, are contrary to the Scriptures, and the practice of the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſcandalize the truth where it is manifeſted in power.</p>
               <p>Are you not covetous? and God doth forbid it, and the Miniſters of Chriſt do forbid it, and ſay,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. 1 Tim. 6.6, 7, 8.</note> Let not covetouſneſs be once named amongſt you, as it becometh Saints, and let your converſation be without covetouſneſs; for covetouſneſs is Idolatry, and draweth the heart from the Lord; and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs is the root of all evil; and you are covetous, (exceeding covetous) the Miniſters of Chriſt ſaid, having food and rayment, therewith let us be content; and the Miniſters of Chriſt laboured to make the Goſpel of Chriſt to be without charge.</p>
               <p>And coveted no mans ſilver nor gold, nor were not greedy of filthy lucre,<note place="margin">Acts 20.32, 33, 34, 35. 2 Pet. 5.1, 2, 3, 4. Gal. 1.11, 12, 15, 16. 2 Cor. 3.6.</note> but ſpoke againſt it, in obedience to the commands of God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt were not taught of man, but of God, they were not made Miniſters by the will of man, but by the will of God, and they were not Miniſters of the letter, but able Miniſters of the ſpirit; and they made full proof of their Miniſtery, and gave no offence in any thing, that their Miniſtery might not be blamed, but in all things approving themſelves as the Miniſters of God, in much patience, in afflictions, in neceſſities, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, in ſtripes, in impriſonments, in tumults, in labours, in watchings, in faſtings, by pureneſs, by knowledge, by long ſufferings, by kindneſs, by the Holy Ghoſt, by love unfained, by the word of Truth, and by the power of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5, 6, 7.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt were blameleſs as the Stewards of God, not ſelf-willed, not ſoon angry, not given to wine, no ſtrikers, not given to ſtrong drink, nor filthy lucre, they were lovers of good men, they were holy, juſt, and temperate; <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.7, 8.<note place="margin">1 Tim 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Mat. 23.8. 1 Cor. 9.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt were not men-pleaſers, neither were they called of men Maſters, but became ſervants to all, in obedience to the Command of Jeſus Chriſt, and they were not perſecuters, but were gentle towards all men, even towards them that did oppoſe them.</p>
               <p>They were examples to the flock, and exhorted others to follow them, ſo far as they followed Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.1, 2. and ſaith he, <hi>Brethren, be ye followers of me,</hi> and mark them that walk ſo as ye have us for an example, <hi>Phil</hi> 3.17.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.17.</note> for ſaith he, many walk of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, that they are enemies of the croſs of Chriſt, whoſe end is deſtruction, whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is their ſhame; who minde earthly things,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18, 19.</p>
               <p>Now conſider the end of your converſation even all ye Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> who profeſs your ſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, ſee where your conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is, are you not altogether earthly, and walk contrary to the holy practice and converſation of the Miniſters of Chriſt, which were examples to the flock in all things? now ſee if you have not loſt your examples, and walk altogether contrary?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:166593:12"/>Firſt, As they had received freely, they ſpoke freely again, and were free from covetouſneſs, they took God to witneſs it, and ſo made the Goſpel of Chriſt free, and not burdenſome.</p>
               <p>Secondly, But you are exceeding covetous, and are hirelings, and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the falſe Prophets, in the ſame ſtate and condition that thoſe were whom the Lord ſent his true Prophets to cry out againſt, then, as he ſendeth to cry out againſt you falſe Prieſts now, which ſcandalize the truth of God; you are all ſcandalous; and if you have that which is your right, you muſt all be caſt out, every one great and ſmall for the higheſt of you in your fleſhly wiſdom and notions, are the higheſt deceivers of the people. Do not your fruits make you manifeſt? Are you not all in the ſame condition that the falſe Prophets were in, that ran, but the Lord never ſent them? do you not look for your gain from you quarter,<note place="margin">Iſa. 56.10, 11.</note> place, and pariſh where you are? as thoſe did that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was ſent to cry out againſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11. Cleer your ſelves if you can; and do you not take Tythes? which neither Ieſus Chriſt nor his true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters did; and ſo act contrary to them, both ſhewing yourſelves to be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, as it is now made manifeſt by your practiſe; ſcandalous you are, all of you Tythe-mongers, and hirelings, and ignorant; you are of the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that they were guided by, that ſpoke for the deceits of the falſe Prophets, and ſo are enemies both to the people of God, and the ways of God, and are guided by a ſpirit of errour; deny it if you can: your works will teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you; and are you not upholders of the traditions and rudiments of the world, which is a prejudice and hinderance of Reformation, and danger of poor ſouls, leading them on in blinde ways, worſhipping the works of your own hands, teaching for doctrine traditions, and rudiments of the world, telling peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that they are ordinances of Chriſt, when they are but your own inventions?</p>
               <p>How dare any of you ſay you are the Miniſters of Chriſt, and act contrary to them? bluſh for ſhames do you not hold up that filthy horrible thing that was committed in the land, which the Lord ſent his true Prophets to cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt? as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>The Prophets did prophecy falſly, and the Prieſts they bore rule by their means,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 5.30, 31.</note> then: But do not all the Prieſts here in York-ſhire ſo now? Following the wayes of <hi>Balaam,</hi> teaching for gifts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,<note place="margin">Iude 11.</note> as they did? Shew me but one in all York-ſhire that does not: Put forth one that is not guilty of it, and cries out againſt it as the true Miniſters did; Come, Where is there one in York-ſhire that goes not on in the wayes of <hi>Cain,</hi> to envy, &amp;c. and that teacheth not for money, or Tythes, and bears not rule by their means? and that ſeeks not for their gain from their quarter, place and pariſh where they are, as the falſe Prophets did? or where is there one that teacheth not for ſome of theſe? Or that teacheth not for gifts or rewards, as <hi>Balaams</hi> Prieſts did, and that cries out of it, and againſt it, as the true Prophets and ſervants of the Lord did?</p>
               <p>Is there not one to be found in all York-ſhire out of the falſe Prophets ſtate, and condition, or elſe found in <hi>Balaams</hi> Prieſts ſtate, and condition, which were all enemies to the Servants of God, and to the ways of God, all minding earthly things, whoſe end is deſtruction? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18, 19. Sift them all, turn them all out, they are ſcandalous men, and ſcandalize the Goſpel of Chriſt which is clear, and free, and hath no ſale ſet upon it, as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2, 3. <hi>Ho every one that thirſteth, come and receive freely, without money or without
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166593:12"/>
price: Why do you ſpend your money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which doth not ſatisfie? Hearken ye diligently to me,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and eat ye that which is good, and your ſouls ſhall live, and I will make with you an everlaſting Covenant, even the ſure mercies of David.</hi> The Servant of the Lord cries, <hi>Come freely,</hi> Iſa. 55. <hi>come eat freely, that your ſouls may live;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> As he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived freely of the Lord, he ſpoke freely again, and directed them to the Lord, as he was taught of the Lord, and as the true Miniſters did, he watched for their ſouls, as one that was to give account unto God.</p>
               <p>But theſe falſe Prieſts, they will do nothing without money, they will have money here in York ſhire for reek paſſing up the chimnies, and for ſervants wages, without money will they do nothing: ſee if that be not their <hi>Diana;</hi> and they are here in York ſhire like unto thoſe falſe Prieſts, that <hi>Micah</hi> the Servant of the Lord was ſent to cry out againſt, <hi>Mica.</hi> 3. ſaith he, <hi>Put into their mouths, and they cry peace, peace,</hi> and ſay we are good Chriſtians, and are the beloved of the Lord; but now that we try them, and put not into their mouths, they ſay, we are Seducers, and Hereticks, and Deluded, and Mad, and they can make ſuch Chriſtians (as they call them) for money, and they can change them, and caſt them out again for want of money; this is the manner of <hi>Balaams</hi> Prieſts here in York-ſhire; and now that we put not into their mouths, they are ſo envious, that if it were in their power, they would deſtroy us, and prepare war againſt us, ſuing ſome at Law, becauſe they will not pay for reek paſſing up their Chimnies,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.40. 1 Cor. 6.1. 2 Ioh. 9. Mich. 3.</note> and threaten others to go to Law with them, which both Jeſus Chriſt and his true Miniſters do forbid, plainly ſhewing themſelves to be none of his; for he that abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. and are like unto thoſe that <hi>Micah</hi> cries out againſt, <hi>Put not into their mouths,</hi> and they prepare war; and now that they are tried, they manifeſt themſelves. All people, try your Prieſts everywhere, and be no longer deceived by them; ſee if York-ſhire Prieſts do not manifeſtly declare themſelves to be amongſt the falſe Prophets, and are ſcandalous all of them, every one, and are ignorant of the Spirit of truth, for they perſecute thoſe in whom it is manifeſted to Rule: and ſee if theſe do not prejudice the calling, and hinder the work of Reformation, as much as in them lies, to the endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering of immortal Souls; but God will cut them off out of the work, they have nothing to do with his Miniſtry, theirs is of man, they are the Miniſters of man and not of God, Enemies to the People of God, and wayes of God, as their fruits do make them manifeſt, every tree being known by its fruits;<note place="margin">Mat. 7.15, 16, 17, 18, 19.</note> they are in the fleſh, the Luſt, the Earth, and the Fall, and perſecute thoſe that are after the ſpirit, who are born again, and worſhip God in Spirit and in truth, as in <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24. Knowing that he ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</p>
               <p>But theſe are of the firſt birth, and draw near to God with their mouth, and lips, but their hearts are far of, having their fear taught by the precepts of men, as thoſe had, which the Lord complained of by his ſervant the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. <hi>ver.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>And are they not upholders and practizers of old Popiſh Ceremonies? do they not uphold the Idols temple ſet up in the time of Popery, or ignorance? for God that made the world, <hi>dwelleth not in temples made with hands, Acts</hi> 7.47, 48, 49. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.24.25. Neither is he worſhipped there with mens hands; and they do worſhip there that which their hearts do imagine, ſprinkling In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166593:13"/>
which is but a Mark of the Beaſt. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.16, 17, 18. and tell the people it is an ordinance of Chriſt, when there is not one word in the Scripture for it;<note place="margin">Gal 3.27. 1 Cor. 12.13. Eph. 4 4, 5, 6. 1 Pet. 1.22.23.</note> They that are Chriſts <hi>have put on Chriſt, and are baptized by one Spirit into one body, where there is but one Faith, one Lord, one Baptiſm, one God, and Father of All, and in All, and through All;</hi> thoſe that are of the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and born again of water and the Spirit; But theſe are ignorant of it.</p>
               <p>And they make uſe of the Popes Law to impriſon by, denying the Law of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.29, 30, 31.</note> or practice of the people of God; as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29 30, 31. when any thing was revealed to him that ſat by, the firſt was to hold his peace, and the other was to ſpeak; but theſe will binde the Spirit of God under a Popiſh Law, and deny the Law of God, as by their fruits it doth appear; and ſo are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders of old Popiſh Ceremonies, teaching for Doctrine the Traditions of men.</p>
               <p>And as the Prieſts here in <hi>York-ſhire</hi> make uſe of the Popiſh Houſe, and the Popiſh Law, to impriſon by, as you may ſee in the Statute-Book, in the 1. of <hi>Mary,</hi> Aſſertion 2. Chap. 3. That which was ſet forth by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> for the upholding of Popiſh Clergy, as is more at large in the book of Eaſter-reckonings, and the Popiſh Ceremonies, are uſed amongſt the Prieſts here in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> as ſprinkling Infants, making Chriſtians (as they ſay) by their Imaginations, ſaying that they enter them then into the Covenant of Chriſt, when they do but mark them in their foreheads as the Beaſt did that <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of in the Revelations, and ſo they uſe their own inventions, calling them Ordinances, but it is but the ordinance of mans beaſtly corrupt Will, and not the Ordinance of Chriſt; neither is there any Scripture for it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Have they not the Popes Doctrine here among them? try them well; do they not keep you ever-learning and never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth? as thoſe that <hi>Paul</hi> foretold of ſhould come in the Laſt dayes, when there would be perilous times, <hi>when men ſhould be lovers of their own ſelves, Covetous, boaſters, proud, falſe accuſers, incontinent, fierce, diſpiſers of thoſe that are good, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God;</hi> and are not the Prieſts here in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> and the Prieſts of the World theſe ſorts of men, as their fruits make them manifeſt, <hi>And have they not a form of Godlineſs, but deny the power thereof?</hi> Is there any Reformation by their Miniſtry? now the Apoſtle bids, <hi>Turn away from ſuch:</hi> 1 Tim. 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then turn away from all your Prieſts,<note place="margin">1 Tim 3.1, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, &amp;c.</note> for they are ſuch that deny the power that reformeth and changeth, and worketh out the old nature, and engrafteth into Chriſt Jeſus, and leadeth up to perfection; they the Prieſts in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> and likewiſe the Prieſts of the World, ſay that they ſhall never be made perfect whilſt they are here, and ſo teach contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and, <hi>If an Angel from Heaven ſhould bring any other Doctrine, we are forbidden to receive it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> Gal. 1.8, 9, 10, 11. They ſay, that they can never over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the body of ſin, nor be made perfect here, and they ſay, <hi>no unclan thing ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> how will they make theſe agree together? try them, ask them if they hold Purgatory, and ſee if this be not the Popes Doctrine? take heed to your ſelves, call them to an account and try them, for they are found falſe in theſe parts, and have deceived us long; but now the Lord ath let us ſee the deceits of them, and they teach for doctrine the Traditions of men, and rudiments of the world, and not after God; who
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166593:13"/>
ſay that you ſhall not overcome your ſins here, <hi>and that no unclean thing</hi> (that cannot be denyed) <hi>ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> then ask them if they would have you go into Purgatory to be made clean; ſee if this be not Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery; and they cry our firſt, as the thief doth, that ſaith, turn theif, turn thief, leaſt they ſhould be taken in the ſnare themſelves: I do teſtifie againſt them all, that they are deceivers, every one, and no Miniſters of Chriſt, neither were they ever ſent of Chriſt, and ſo they ſcandalize the Truth of God, and hinder the work of Reformation, as much as in them lies, and do endanger poor ſouls, and are (as <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſpeaks of them) Murtherers, and murder the pure ſeed in themſelves and in others, where there is any appearance of it, and deny the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt taught the people and preſſed them to perfection. and ſaid, <hi>Be ye perfect, as your Heavenly Father is perfect,</hi> Mat. 5.48.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.48.</note> and the Apoſtle taught the people, as he was taught of God, and he preſſed them to perfection, and ſaid, <hi>Let as many as are perfect be thus minded, and the reſt to preſs on to perfection,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.15. Gal. 1.15, 16. Col. 1.25, 26, 27, 28, 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. this was the Doctrine that the holy men of God preached, <hi>And the Apoſtle who was made a Miniſter, according to the diſpenſation of the grace of God that was given him, which was Chriſt revealed in him, whom we preach, warning every man, everywhere, and teaching every man in all wiſdome, that he might preſent every man perfect in Chriſt.</hi> Col. 1.25.26, 27, 28, 29. This was the doctrine of Chriſt, to preſs them on to be perfect, as their Father which is in heaven is perfect; the Apoſtle who was his true Miniſter, did preſs to the ſame thing, to preſent every man perfect in Chriſt; &amp; the Prieſts here in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and the Prieſts of the World, the Miniſtry of Antichriſt, or of man, and not of God, ſay that they ſhall never overcome their ſins, and ſo keeps them ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth; ſaying that they ſhall never be perfect here; and ſee if this be not the Popes doctrine; It is not the doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt, nor his Apoſtle, who ſaid he did ſtrive, labouring mightily according to the power of God, to preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.28, 29. and the ſame man of God,<note place="margin">Gal. 1 8 9.</note> who had the power of God working in him, ſaid, He that brings any other doctrine, let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed; which thoſe Prieſts do deny, as by their fruits, and doctrine it doth appear, in which Doctrine is the doctrine of the Devil, that doth not purifie and purge the Conſcience from dead works to ſerve the living God, which doctrine is accurſed, and they cry out of Popery and Prophaneſs; now ſee if they be not as he that cries, turn theif, turn theif; to ſet the people to look on ſome other, that he in tht mean time may eſcape; and thoſe Prieſts cry out to the Parliament of Popery and prophaneſs, and live in the ſame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they cry out againſt, and would be blinding them with their flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ſetting them to look on others, whiſt they themſelves ſhould eſcape; but if they do but turn about, and look on with a ſingle eye, they may have a plain made here to caſt out all the Prieſts in <hi>York ſhire,</hi> and do them Juſtice, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their own deſire; light is riſen out of darkneſs and ſees them to be all ſcandalous, and Ignorant, and Enemies both to the people of God, and the ways of God, and upholders and practiſers of the aboliſhed Popiſh Ceremonies, and are hinderers of right reformation, and deſtroyers of poor ſouls, as much as in them lieth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And theſe Prieſts, they put <hi>Davids</hi> Conditions into rime and meeter, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166593:14"/>
into the houſe of <hi>Rimmon</hi> to worſhip, where they ſing lyes in Hypocriſie, ſaying, All my bones ſhake, and all my fleſh trembles, when they lye: and lying is diſhonour to the Lord; and they ſay, O Lord my righteouſneſs, when they themſelves are the ſervants of Sin and plead for it, and teach the people to lye, calling that the ſervice of God; but lying is of the Devil, and he is the Father of lyes, and they teach the People to ſing, and ſay, <hi>O Lord I am not puft in minde, I have no ſcornful eye:</hi> when they are puft in ſcorn and deriſion, and ſo ſing lyes to the diſhonour of God, all lyes, howling and lying; when they read <hi>Davids</hi> conditions, they read them with hats on, and when they turn them into rime and meeter, they put their hats off, and lye ſinging, and ſetting that nature on ſinging, and to rejoyce; which is for the curſe, and ſo worſhip the works of their own hands, following the Imaginations of their own hearrs, and take a glaſs and ſpeak an hour by their old Author ſtudyed ſpirit, and their glaſs ſtanding by, as if the word of the Lord was to be bound to an hour,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.15. Rev. 14.1, 2, 3.</note> day, or place; ſee if this be not errour, or Popery, and hold it not up, be not deceived, God will not be mocked.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let him that ſings, ſing with the Spirit, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> to know what he ſings; They that are redeemed from the Earth, ſhall ſing new Songs, which none can ſing but thoſe that are redeemed out of the Fall up to the Lord God, <hi>and to the Lamb, to Praiſe him for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let not your Prieſts deceive you, and deſtroy your ſouls any longer, and keep you under Popery, Atheiſm and Ignorance of the Spiritual Miniſtry; Chriſt is a Myſterie, and none know him, but they to whom he is revealed: put out all your Prieſts, they all deceive you, every one.</p>
               <p>And that you may know the truth, wait upon the Lord for teaching, who is the Teacher of all his by his Spirit, and the miniſtration is powerful, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the ſoul out of the Fal up to God, and to reform and change your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and diſpoſitions, which will guide you, and lead you into the way of peace, to know the Lord, to gather out of all the ways and works of darkneſs, Atheiſm and Popery, Covetouſneſs and Prophaneſs, which all are given to Preiſts, and People, that live in their firſt nature, and know not God; <hi>who is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of purer eyes then to behold Iniquity; who is a conſuming fire, and is both the heart-ſearcher and tryer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petition.</note> 
                  <hi>and will burn up the wicked in the indignation of his Ire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, by whom we have believed, whoſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours have been ſo profitable, and are yet ſo neceſſary to the Church of God, and whoſe reputations and encouragements ought to be ſo dear unto us, are daily laden with contempt and reproach, diſturbed in the diligent and peaceable execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their office, by evil and unreaſonable men, and alſo undermined in their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and maintenance: whereby the courſe of the Goſpel is much hindered, and the ſpirit of Gods people, (nay we doubt not to ſay) the Spirit of God himſelf is grieved and vexed to ſee the precious Ordinances of Chriſt trodden under foot,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, by whom we have believed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>That the Miniſters of <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> or the Miniſters of the World, are the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Anſw. <hi>1.</hi> The Prieſts Practiſe.</note> as their fruits do make them manifeſt; and their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry is of man, and not of God, and the Faith that is ſpoken of is corrupt, for it doth not purifie, but worketh into Pride, Covetouſneſs, oppreſſion, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, luſt and revenge, hatred, backbiting, ſcornfulneſs, cruelty, malice, debate, deceit, malignity and envy, drunkenneſs, lying and ſwearing; becauſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166593:14"/>
of oaths, the Land mourns, and pride ſwels, and Covetouſneſs, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and grinding the faces of the poor, and theſe are the fruits of the reprobate, and are Ordinances of Antichriſt and not of Chriſt, and they are all gone out of the way, both Prieſts and people, and the people are deſtroyed for lack of knowledge; becauſe thou haſt rejected knowledge, ſaith the Lord, I will alſo reject thee; that thou ſhalt be no Prieſt to me; ſeeing thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the Law of thy God, I will alſo forget thy children; as they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, ſo they ſinned againſt me, ſaith the Lord; and as it was then, ſo it is now; therefore thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will change their glory into ſhame, for they eat up the ſin of my people, and they ſet their heart to do wickedly;</hi> it is not now made manifeſt by their fruits? for there is like Prieſt like people,<note place="margin">Hoſea 4 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>I will puniſh them for their wayes, and reward them their doings, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Hoſ. 4.6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is with the Prieſts now, as it was with the falſe Prieſts and falſe Prophets; and the people now, as it was with the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after they had backſlid. and broken the Covenant of the Lord; their ſins teſtifie againſt them to their faces now, as theirs did then, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.5. <hi>They call the proud happy: and they that work wickedneſs are ſet up; and they that tempt God are even delivered.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.15.</note> Mal. 3.15. as it was then ſo it is now, in this generation; and the Prieſts of the World are contrary to Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who were his true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in all things. 1. They are exceeding proud, and are called of men Maſters, which Jeſus Chriſt hath taught his to deny: <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.8. and herein they walk contrary to the Scripture, and the command of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſhew the ſpirit of errour, and are no Miniſters of Chriſt, that do not abide in his Doctrine, but are of Antichriſt, and are Lords over Gods heritage;<note place="margin">Mat. 23.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> Proud Phariſees they are, and ſit in the ſame ſeat, and act the ſame things as they did; they have the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies, as the Scribes and Phariſees had, which were enemies to Ieſus Chriſt; they love the greetings in markets, as they did, and to be called of men Maſters, as they were, and ſuffer men to worſhip them with cap and knee, and are enemies to Ieſus Chriſt, as the Scribes and Phariſees were, and hold up that which he came to throw down, and ſo walk contrary to Ieſus Chriſt; herein they ſhew themſelves to be Antichriſts, and of the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e generation that perſecuted Chriſt when he came in the fleſh, as they do now that he is appearing in Spirit, and the chief Prieſts were the greateſt perſecuters of him then, as the Prieſts of <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> are now, who follow their ſteps.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are exceeding covetous, and burden and oppreſs poor people,<note place="margin">Acts 20.33, 34, 35. 1 Cor. 4.11, 12, 13. 1 Cor. 9.15, 16, 17, 18. Gal. 1.10. Jam. 2.1, 2.</note> and are light and wanton, living in pleaſures and wantoneſs upon earth, which the true Miniſters of Chriſt did forbid, as in all things they were good examples to the people; but theſe are evil examples, and walk contrary both to the Scriptures, and the practiſe of Chriſt, and his true Miniſters; herein they ſhew the ſpirit of errour, and are enemies to the Truth of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>They are men-pleaſers,</hi> all the Prieſts of the world, <hi>and have mens perſons in admiration becauſe of advantage, denying the Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Iames 2.1, 2. Gal. 1.10. which the true Miniſters of Chriſt did practiſe; herein they walk contrary to the Scripture, and ſhew the Spirit of errour, and are enemies to the truth of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Prieſts of the World, or the Miniſters of man and of Antichriſt, they are blamable, and are ſoon angry, and are given to wine, ſtrikers, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:166593:15"/>
are given altogether to filthy lucre,<note place="margin">Jer. 23.26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32. Joh. 1.1, 2. &amp;c. Joh. 17.14, 15, 16, 17. Jer. 23.29. Heb. 4.12. 1 Pet. 1.22, 23. Rom. 6. 1 Cor. 6.11. 1 Pet. 1.25. Jam. 1.21, 22. Col. 1.1. 2 Cor. 3.6. Gal. 1.11, 12. Eph. 1.1. 2 Tim. 1.1. Mat. 23. Mat. 26. Jer. 23.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. Jer. 23.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. Jer. 23.1. Jer. 5.23, 24, 25, &amp;c. Hoſea. 4.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. Iſa. 59. Iſa. 29.9, 10, 11, &amp;c. Gal. 1.8, 9. Mal. 2. to the 10. <hi>The two Seeds, one of the Fleſh, and the other of the Spirit.</hi>
                  </note> contrary to the Miniſters of Chriſt, as in <hi>Titus</hi> 1.7. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. walking contrary to the Scripture, and are guided by the ſpirit of error.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Prieſts of the world and their Miniſtry is not of God, but of man; they are the Miniſters of man, and not of God, and are no Miniſters of the Spirit, but are of the imaginary wayes; what they do conceive of, or imagine, that they hold forth, and know not the word of life, which is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, that ſanctifieth, and purifieth Soul and Body, which word is inviſible, and is as a fire, and a hammer, and is quick, and powerfull, which is the power of God that killeth the old nature, and purgeth out the old leaven, and raiſeth up the immortal Soul out of death to praiſe the Lord. And they that do Adminiſter it, are cleanſed, and waſhed, juſtified and ſanctified by it, which word endureth for ever, being the ingrafted word, that is able to ſave the ſouls of thoſe that know the Miniſtration of it, and the Miniſters of it were, and are able Miniſters of the Spirit, not taught of man, but by the will of God, and adminiſter to that which is kept in the death, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſeed, which the Miniſters of the world are ignorant of, but are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuters of thoſe that hold forth the word of life now, as the Jews and Scribes, and Phariſees, chief Prieſts, and Elders of the people were, and they ſpeak a divination of their own brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord, and their Miniſtry will never ſatisfie nor purifie one ſoul; it hath been long, but here is no redemption, nor Sanctification by it; Nay, they ſay themſelves that it will never ſanctifie them whilſt they are here, and by their fruits it doth ſo appear, and ſo it doth not profit the people at all; they teach for Doctrine traditions, and rudiments of the world, and they are all confuſed, ſo many men, ſo many minds; when as the Miniſters of Chriſt were and are all of one heart, and one minde, who were taught of God, and are Miniſters of the Spirit, and not of the letter, or of man, as the Prieſts of the world, and all thoſe here in <hi>York-ſhire</hi> are, and are contrary both to Chriſt, and his true Miniſters, and load his Servants with Reproachings, and Revilings, and are Enemies both to him and his, and they and their Miniſtry is accurſed, for it is contrary both to Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and doth neither ſanctifie, nor purifie, but keeps in the luſt of the fleſh, and in the fall.</p>
               <p>There are two ſeeds, one after the fleſh, as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was, and the other after the Spirit, and by promiſe, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was; and they that are after the fleſh, they perſecute them that are after the ſpirit, and they that are after the ſpirit, or by promiſe, are made not onely to believe, but alſo to ſuffer what the Lord ſhall permit, or ſee good; and they that are of the promiſed ſeed are of <hi>Abraham</hi> now, and are born again, one Seed, one Faith, one God, one Father, one Baptiſm, one Bread, one Body, all one, and in one, Baptized by one Spirit into that one body, which is ſpiritual, and made to drink into one Spirit, and their faith doth purifie them, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them out of their old nature, and ingrafteth them into the Vine, which is Chriſt Jeſus, the Vine of the Lords free love, and being all one in Chriſt Jeſus, ſet and ingrafted into their own Vine, the natural branches being cut off, thoſe that are Jews outward, and not inward, who live in the wild-O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, and in their natural ſtock, or ſtate, or condition, know them not who are in the true Vine, being made partakers of the Divine nature, their faith ſtanding out of the wiſdom of mans words in the power of God,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:166593:15"/>
groweth with an increaſe, making fruifull, being in the Vine, the fruits of true faith do ſhew it forth, as Vertue, and Knowledge, Temperance, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Godlineſs, brotherly kindneſs, and charity, which maketh fruitfull in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; ſo ſhall all men know, ſaith he, <hi>That ye are my Diſciples, if ye love one another,</hi> continue in my love: for faith without works is dead, as the worlds faith is, or the fruits of the firſt ſeed, which is after the fleſh, and they that are in the fleſh, their old corrupt nature, and in the wild Olive, they cannot pleaſe God, and their faith ſtandeth without in the wiſdom of mans words, and not in the power of God, which worketh a Reformation, and a change, but as they are in the fall, their fruits make them manifeſt, and their faith is corrupt, it doth not purifie their conſcience from dead works, and ſo they believe in that which thier prieſts lead them into for good, as ſay the Petitioners, we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in them for good, like Prieſts, like People, as in <hi>Hoſeas</hi> time, <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 4. and all live in one nature, that are in the fall, and are under the curſe, in their old nature, both Prieſts and people, and the Prieſts are evil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to the people.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Prieſts, they live in Pride, and the people they believe,<note place="margin">The Prieſts are evil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</note> that if they may be proud that are their leaders, they may follow their examples, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſuitable to their earthly hearts, and ſo they believe in them, as they ſay, for good, calling good evil, and evil good; but the woe is to ſuch.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Prieſts they live in Covetouſneſs, and the people they follow their examples, and are all given to Covetouſneſs, both Prieſts and people, and love it, and believe it is good, becauſe it is ſuitable to their earthly hearts, and that is the good that they believe in them for, all feeding daily on the forbidden fruit, for both Pride and Covetouſneſs is forbidden, and thoſe that live in it, both Prieſts, and People, are in the broad way, in the fall, and under the curſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Prieſts live in rayling, and lying, and ſpeaking evil of that which they know not, and they live in pleaſures and wantonneſs, and heady-high-mindedneſs, Luſt, and revenge to perſecution, oppreſſion, and grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faces of the poor, and ſee if theſe be not fruits of darkneſs, and whether they do not live in them, and the tree is known by its fruits, and if this be not Atheiſm, Ignorance, Blindneſs, Deluſion, and Herreſie, and errs from the truth; for they are no fruits of the Spirit, but of the fleſh, and of the ſeed of the Serpent, whoſe head is yet unbruiſed in them that act thoſe things: And the People they follow the example of the Prieſts, and believe that if they do ſuch things, that are teachers, and leaders of them, they may do the ſame, and follow them as Examples, and becauſe thoſe things are delightſome to the fleſh, they love them, and believe in them for good, and would not leave the evil of their doings, but cry out againſt thoſe that ſpeaks againſt them for their ungodly deeds.</p>
               <p>And becauſe they cannot but declare againſt their deceits in ſpeaking the truth, they cry out, ſaying, that they lade them with contempt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and diſturb them, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But the time is come that they cannot endure ſound Doctrine;<note place="margin">The Prieſts cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſound Doctrine.</note> are not the Prieſts here in York-ſhire, in the ſame ſtate and condition that the falſe Prieſts, and falſe Prophets were in, whom the Lord ſent his true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:166593:16"/>
to cry out againſt then, as he ſendeth to cry out againſt theſe now? <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was ſent to cry out againſt them, and called them dumb dogs, yea greedy dogs, ſhepherds that could not underſtand, that never had enough, for they did every one look for their gain from their quarter, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 56.10, 11. and becauſe he ſpoke the truth, he was hated of them; as thoſe do hate the Servants of the Lord now, that teſtifie againſt their deceits, and diſturb them, breaking their carnall peace, and falſe reſt, and now they cry out againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> he was ſent to cry out againſt them, and ſaid that they held up a filthy, and a horrible thing; for they preached for hire, and did bear rule over the people by their means, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30. and do they not ſo now? was not <hi>Jeremy</hi> lade with contempt for declaring the truth, and put in the Priſon, and in the Dungeon? and am I become your Enemy, becauſe I tell you the truth? doth that lade you, and diſturb you, or do not you lade the ſervants of the Lord, that are ſent to tell you of your deceits, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveableneſs, and render them odious to the People? but the Lord will clear up the Innocency of his People, and take away the names of reproach from them, and give you the cup of his fury, that you may drink the dreggs of it, and be aſhamed of the evil of your doings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Malachi,</hi> He was ſent to the Prieſts to tell them that their bleſſings were curſt, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. and you are now found in the ſame ſtate and condition; doth truth lade you, and diſturb you, and break your peace? It muſt be ſo, for God is againſt you, and you are thoſe that cauſe the truth to ſuffer, and lade it by reproaches, and revilings, and perſecutions, as your fruits make it manifeſt, and ſo you muſt drink the cup of trembling, and aſtoniſhment; for <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be a burdenſome ſtone to all Nations; for the Spirit of God is grieved by you that burden, and oppreſs poor creatures, and are never ſatisfied, crying out for means for your bellies, making your bellies your Gods, ſeeking after earth and earthly things; Whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is their ſhame, who mind earthly things, perſecuting, and impriſoning, and ſhamefully entreating thoſe that are ſent to preach the glad tidings of the Goſpel, and you fill up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your fathers Iniquities, as your fruits do witneſs againſt you, that you are they that ſtay the righteous, and perſecute the Innocent, and are drawing upon your heads wrath without remedy, even wrath to the utmoſt; for he will plague the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet, and burn the whore with fire, and confound the wiſdom of the wiſe, and bring to nought the counſel of the prudent, that he may reveale himſelf to babes, and teach them the knowledge of his truth, <hi>for he will rule all Nations with his Iron-rod, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, the Lord God omnipotent, ever praiſed be his name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Petition.</note>Laſtly, <hi>They take boldneſs to repreſent, that the liberty granted by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in matters of Religion, and the worſhip of God, is much abuſed, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Popery and prophaneneſs, contrary to your intentions in the ſame,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It grieveth theſe perſecuting Prieſts that any liberty ſhould be granted for the Truth to be declared, leſt that their deceits ſhould be laid open; and are troubled that the Parliament ſhould ſee beyond them, to give ſome liberty, that truth may not alwayes be bound under the powers of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:166593:16"/>
darkneſs ruling in the proud Prieſts; but light is riſing in Parliament, and people, to ſee the deceits of the Prieſts, though they would be giving meanings by their old-author ſtudied ſpirit, got out of old Authors at the Univerſity, where the fountain is corrupted, full of dead mens bones, and now it ſtinks, now that their deceit is diſcovered how they have deceived the people in the night time, the time of darkneſs, whilſt the Myſterie of iniquity bore rule in man, now light is riſen, and is ariſing to ſee how they have a long time blinded the people in giving meanings to the Scriptures, which are true as they ſpeak, who do come to ſee them fulfilled, can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it, as there are many in thoſe parts can bear teſtimony to the ſame; and now that the ſubtile Foxes are beaten out of that hole, they would make the Parliament believe that there ſtands need of a meaning to be given to their late act, or grant for liberty in matters of Religion, as if they knew not what they did intend in the thing, without they give them a meaning to their intentions, but becauſe it is contrary to their intention, that is the reaſon that they would not have any to know any thing, but what they ſuggeſt, or put into their brain; but brain knowledge is dying, and now the Prieſts are crying to Magiſtrates to help, to uphold them; but as light doth ariſe in the hearts of the Parliament, they will be ready to put out their dim lights, and give ſuch grants for liberty of Conſcience, that truth may be declared in every place; that which is revealed in ſecret, ſhall be declared on the houſe top, and that will make a free paſſage for truth to be declared; and ſo the corrupt fountain of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> which is under the curſe will have a ſtop, and then there will be an effectuall courſe taken, for removing of ſcandalous Miniſters, that run from God to be taught of man, and ſo all caſt out, that none may ſpeak but as they do receive their words from the Lord, which runs out of the pure Fountain, and that is under the bleſſing of the Almighty, where there is no burthening of poor people for carnal means, ſeeking after the love and friendſhip, and honor of the world, and kingdom of the world, as the Prieſts of the world do, that are in the ſtate and condition of infidelity, Atheiſm, and profaneneſs, and dare not truſt God, but diſhonour him. And they are worthy all to be removed, and caſt out; the time draweth nigh, wherein righteouſneſs ſhall run down all our ſtreets, and knowledge ſhall fill the earth as the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cover the Sea, and righteouſneſs ruling in Magiſtrates, and Juſtice and Equity ſet up, which we honor in our ſouls, and thoſe that are the acters of it, and we rejoyce to ſee the Lord declaring his free love through his poor deſpiſed creatures, and binding up the broken hearted, but we deny the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> for they have a long time deceived us, and now it is our duty to cry out againſt their deceits, that all people may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of them, and ſee what they are profited by them, and what Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is amongſt them; are they not all confuſed, and live in conceivings, and imaginations? but the Lord is binding his Law upon the Spirits of his people, which will be ſuch battlements of purity, that deceits and deceivers will not be able to enter into the inward Court, but will be kept without, and trodden underfoot, and Popiſh and profane perſons caſt out; &amp; Proud, Covetous, Envious, Malicious Prieſts with their ſubtilties cannot enter any more with their deceiveableneſs, and craftineſs, whereby they lie in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:166593:17"/>
wait to deceive poor people to the diſhonor of God, in deſpiſing his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which is his power, even the power of God unto Salvation; which power they being ignorant of, they do pollute his Sabboths in doing their own work, and not his; ſpeaking their own words, and thinking their own thoughts, which thoſe do not that are entred into their reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. As theſe do, that ſell their wares at great rates, and compell people to buy, and if they have not money to give them, then they ſue, and go to Law, and break the Law of God, and if any come to declare what God hath done for his ſoul, as <hi>David</hi> did, though it be after that he hath ended his ſtage-play, contrary to the Grant for the eaſing of burdned conſciences, he cries, Take him away, and have him to priſon, and take boldneſs to break the Laws of the Land, and run away himſelf, but the tryall he will not ſtand; and this is the practice of ſeveral of the Prieſts here in York-ſhire, when the Lord ſends to any of them, and thus they prove themſelves to be the Miniſters of man, and not of God; but he will bruiſe them with his Iron rod.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let all that love the Lord, bleſs the Lord, praiſe him, and magnifie him for ever: The Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our Law-giver, the Lord is our King, and doth us teach, preſerve, and keep, and out of their cruelties ſave, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver, to him alone that ſits upon his throne, ruling by his power, each day, and eeke each hour, be all praiſe, honor, and glory, for ever, and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hallelujah to the higheſt: The Lord raigneth, let the earth rejoyce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All ye Saints of the Lord, bleſs ye the Lord, praiſe him, and magnifie him for ever;</hi> and let Juſtice, and equity be ſet up, and righteouſneſs eſtabliſhed; ſo ſhall you have the bleſſing of the Lord upon all your counſells, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and rejoyce in him for evermore.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:166593:17"/>
            <head>An exhortation to the Magiſtrates.</head>
            <p>AWake awake you Magiſtrates and Rulers, and fear the Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and do that which is Juſt, have mercy and walk humbly with your God, and do Juſtice without partiality: O ſtand in the Counſel of the Lord, and beware of looking out to the Egyptian ſtudies for Counſel: and you which are ſet up to be Rulers, caſt out all your old Laws, that are contrary to the Law of God, and eſtabliſh Laws according to the Law of God, that God may be glorified in you, bringing forth the fruits of Righteouſneſs: Beware of being countenancers of evil doers, and puniſhing the innocent, poor, and harmeleſs, and let all ſuch who are ſound ſcandalous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which profeſs Chriſt in words, not abiding in his doctrine, let them be caſt out, for his Goſpel is the power of God unto Salvation, and not their vain In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, Imaginations, Repetitions, and Divinations of their own Brain; Ceaſe from holding them up, the Lord is againſt them, for he alone is come to teach his children himſelf, who is our King, Lawgiver, and Judge, to whom be all praiſe and thanksgiving now and for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Aldam, By the dark World called a Quaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="exhortation">
            <head>An Exhortation to all People that have a deſire to know the Truth, that the Truth may make them free.</head>
            <p>EVery one that hath a deſire to know the truth, that the truth may ſet you free, mind the light of God in you, that ſhews you ſin, and evil, that which checks you when you do amiſs, either when you lye, or ſwear, or are Proud, or Covetous, or Oppreſs, or Envy, or Hate, or Backbite one another, or uſe any deceit, there is ſomething in you that will check you, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:166593:18"/>
tell you that you ſhould not do ſo, if you hearken to it; that which ſhews you your vain thoughts, and wondering deſires, and wicked Imaginations, if you hearken to it, and let it guide your mindes, it will turn them within, and ſo ſhew you how you have ſpent your time, and bring you to conſider of your wayes, and your doings, that you may forſake that which is evil, and turn to the Lord, that he may have mercy upon you; this light within, if you hearken to it, it will not ſuffer you to do any wrong to any man, but to do to all as you would be done by; and obeying it, it will teach you to deny your ſelves of Pride, and Covetouſneſs, and Oppreſſion, and Drunkenneſs, and Lying, and Swearing, and Vain talk, and Fooliſh jeſting, and all vain delights and pleaſures whatſoever; and minding this light within, to be obedient to it, it will croſs your earthly wills, and turn you out of the luſt, and filth of the fleſh, and lead you out of all the worlds wayes, and words, and cuſtoms, and faſhions, and worſhips, and delights, and vanities whatſoever, and bring you to delight in the Lord, to do his will, in yeilding obedience to his commands, in what the light doth require of you to be done, that you may caſt off the works of darkneſs, as this light within makes them manifeſt to you; This light within you, will not ſuffer you to eat and drink to make your ſelves wanton, if you hearken to it, and let it guide your minds; this light within, will not let you wear apparel to make your ſelves proud, and burden and oppreſs poor creatures, if you hearken to it; and here is your teacher, this light, obeying it; and here is your condemnation, this light diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying it; this light is not without you, a Chapter or a Verſe, but the light is within, as it was in them that ſpoke forth the Chapters; ye have a light, to the whith ye do well to take heed, as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day-ſtar ariſe in your hearts: Take heed to that light, leſt you be condemned by it: obeying it, it will ſhew you the way to Salvation; diſobeying this light, it will condemn you.</p>
            <p>Now you have time, prize it, and take heed of rejecting the Counſel and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Lord to your ſouls, as you will anſwer it before the Lord: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, and lay it to heart; This is the day of your viſitation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VVritten by a Husbandman.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
